Guide to the Houston Gorilla Girls
University of Houston Libraries
Houston Gorilla Girls Records
1985-2000
1988-1997
02/2010-006
Gorilla Girls (Group of artists: Houston, Tex.)
10.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes the records, written works, collected writings, and photographs that document the development of the Houston Gorilla Girls, an anonymnous women’s art collective that protested sexism and racism in the art world from the 1987 to the late nineties. There are nine series, spanning from 1985 to 2000 which are entitled as follows: Correspondence; Organizational Documents and Photographs; Propaganda; Diverse Works Installation: Another Dead Horse; Rice University Installation at the Sewell Gallery: “Been Down So Long Feels Like Up To Me”; Other Gorilla Girls Installations and Shows: 1988-1997; Miscellaneous Clippings, Photographs, Articles, and Correspondence; New York City Guerrilla Girls; and Guerrilla/Gorilla Girls, Other Cities.
Historical Note:
In the Spring of 1985, the walls of Lower Manhattan’s Soho and West Village neighborhoods became plastered with “Public Service Announcements” railing against sexism in the art world. At the bottom of each poster was stamped:
“The Guerilla Girls
Conscience of the art world.”
The anonymous art collective of gorilla-masked women that was behind the feminist propaganda campaign began appearing soon thereafter at well-known museums and Galleries in New York City. The enigmatic hominid-clad protesters quickly gained notoriety and copycat groups began springing up in cities throughout North America.
In May of 1987, one such group, the self-styled Houston “Gorilla Girls,” made their first “hit” at the Glassell School of Art in Houston’s Museum District. They then went on to demonstrate against what they perceived as sexism and racism at high-profile Houston art venues such as the Menil, the Museum of Fine Arts Houston, and the Lawndale Arts Center.
The Houston Gorilla Girls’ string of “hits,” performances, and installations ran from 1987 to 1997, when they performed a final show in Verona, Italy at the Villa Carlotta. During their period of activity they became a fixture of the Houston arts scene and are credited with helping open its doors to more female and minority artists. To date, the identities and whereabouts of the Houston Gorilla Girls remain unknown.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Gorilla Girls (Group of artists: Houston, Tex.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Brochures; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Greeting cards; Manuscripts (document genre); Photographs; Postcards; Typescripts
Topical Term:
Art -- Texas -- Houston; Artists -- Texas -- Houston; Feminism; Feminism and art; Feminists; Women artists -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Houston Women’s Caucus for Art Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=335
Womynspace Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=430
Women in the Visual and Literary Arts Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=332
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the records, written works, collected writings, and photographs that document the development of the Houston Gorilla Girls, an anonymnous women’s art collective that protested sexism and racism in the art world from the 1987 to the late nineties. There are nine series, spanning from 1985 to 2000 which are entitled as follows: Correspondence; Organizational Documents and Photographs; Propaganda; Diverse Works Installation: Another Dead Horse; Rice University Installation at the Sewell Gallery: “Been Down So Long Feels Like Up To Me”; Other Gorilla Girls Installations and Shows: 1988-1997; Miscellaneous Clippings, Photographs, Articles, and Correspondence; New York City Guerrilla Girls; and Guerrilla/Gorilla Girls, Other Cities.
The collection is housed in ten boxes, eight of which contain original costumes and installation material.
Detailed List of Contents
- Organizational Documents and Photographs, id123771
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains ten folders comprised of documents and photographs that narrate the development of the Houston Gorilla Girls in financial statements, clippings, posters, correspondence and photographs.
  - Houston Gorilla Girls Organizational Correspondence, 1987-1988; id123787 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook containing miscellaneous notes and correspondence, undated; id123788 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Federal Non-Profit I.D., 1989; id123789 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements and Receipts (Central Bank): Financial documentation, 1989-1992; id123790 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Donations by the Gorilla Girls: donation-related documents, 1988; id123791 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Influences: Clippings, manuscript and posters, 1987-1993; id123792 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gorilla Girls Houston Garden Shots: Black and White and Color Prints, 1987; id123793 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New Years Eve 1990: black and white prints, id123794 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gorilla Pictures and Cartoons: clipped gorilla images, undated; id123795 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous photographs: black and white and color prints, undated; id123796 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, id123772
  This series contains seven folders of typescript and manuscript correspondence along with original mailing lists between the Gorilla Girls and members of the arts community in Houston and internationally.
  - Galleries and Museums, 1987-1991; id123798 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence/Women: typescript and manuscript (1 of 2), 1988-1993; id123799 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence/Women: typescript and manuscript (2 of 2), 1987-2000; id123800 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Patricia Johnson Houston Chronicle: typescript correspondence, 1988; id123801 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters of Interest: typescript and manuscript correspondence, 1988-1990; id123802 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mailing Lists: sheets of labled addresses, 1990; id123803 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cultural Arts Council of Houston (CACH) correspondence, 1992; id123804 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Propaganda, id123773
  This series contains two sub-series that document the ways in which the Gorilla Girls tried to institute change through artistic persuasion. Housed within are photographs, correspondence, costume pieces, and original protest placards and flyers.
  - Printed and Photographed Material, id123780
    - Glassel - 1st Appearance: photocopied protest material, negatives, and articles, 5/28/1987; id123806 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Mail-Outs-Gallery Hits: progaganda posters, 1987-1990; id123807 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Report Card: manuscript, news releases, and poster templates, 1990; id123808 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - CACH Action: mailing lists and propaganda placards, undated; id123809 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Statistics: flyers and protest placard, undated; id123810 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - MFA Houston “Hit,”: clippings and other printed material, 1988; id123811 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Museum of Fine Arts Houston “Hit”: Photographs and slides, 1988; id123812 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Davis and McClain Gallery “Hit” Photographs, undated; id123813 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Menil “Hit”: articles, brochures, photographs, and protest materials, 1988-1991; id123814 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - New Year Mail Out: posters and clippings, 1990; id123815 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Costume Pieces, id123781
    One box of gorilla masks, rubber stamps, and other costume material.
- Diverse Works Installation: “Another Dead Horse”, id123774
  This series contains two sub-series, comprised of 13 folders and seven boxes of documentation and artifacts pertaining to the 1998 Gorilla Girls installation at the Diverse Works Art Space.
  - Installation Documentation, id123782
    - Planning Material: notebooks and paper patterns, 1987; id123818 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Expenses notebook, patterns, brochures, and manuscript financial documentation, 1987-1988; id123819 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, calendars, and financial documents, 1986-1988; id123820 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - Clippings, 1988; id123822 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Photographs, 1987; id123823 (Box 1, Folder 33-36)
    - Slides, 1987; id123827 (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
    - Diverse Works DVD’s, dubbed from video casettes, 1988; id123830 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Installation Artifacts, id123783
    This sub-series includes two sub-sub-series comprised of six boxes of 78 stuffed gorillas and one box of 12 caricature cut-outs that were part of the “Another Dead Horse” exhibit.
    - Stuffed Gorillas, id123784
      Seventy-eight total, stored in six boxes.
    - Caricature Cutouts, id123785
      Twelve caricature cut-outs, 1 collage piece, 1 paper maché gorilla doll, 3 cutout quotation placards, G.G. Installation cassette tape, and G.G.-1991 Burning Bush cassette tape.
- Rice University Installation at the Sewell Gallery: “Been Down So Long Feels Like Up To Me”, id123775
  This series contains seven folders comprised of the financial and planning documents, clippings,photographs and other materials related to the Gorrilla Girls’ installation at Rice University’s Sewell Gallery entitled, “Been Down So Long Feels Like Up To Me.”
  - Correspondence, 1991; id123839 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Financial documents, 1991-1992; id123840 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Installation schematics and exhibit material, 1987-1992; id123841 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1987-1993; id123842 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Photographs, undated; id123844 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Slides, undated; id123845 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Other Gorilla Girls Installations and Shows, 1988-1997; id123776
  This series contains nine folders composed of printed material that document various art shows and installations undertaken by Gorilla Girls Houston between 1988 and 1997, including one show that was put on in Verona, Italy.
  - Art Car Parade: Color prints, 1988; id123847 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Foto Fest 1990: Correspondence, brochures, slides and photographs, 1989-1990; id123848 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Foto Fest 1990 Banner: Large paint on burlap banner, id123849 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - The Orange Show: Typed correspondence, 1989-1991; id123850 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Houston Women’s Caucus for Art (HWCA) Firehouse Show, “Buring Bush,” installation material and clippings, 1991; id123851 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - HWAC Firehouse Show, “Burning Bush” Installation Material, 1991; id123852 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Lawndale: Press releases and brochures, 1993; id123853 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Verona, Italy Show at the Villa Carlotta: color prints, 1997-1998; id123854 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Gorilla Girls Press: Articles, guest-message booklets, certificates, and flyers, 1987-2000; id123855 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Photographs, Articles, and Correspondence, id123777
  This series contains six folders of printed material and photographs that members of the Houston Gorilla Girls saved to be used in installations and as reference material for panel discussions.
  - Irritating Bullshit: photocopied nude photograph, 1987; id123857 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Feminist quotes, typescript and manuscript, 1987; id123858 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Feminist Clippings, 1987; id123859 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Feminist Clippings, undated; id123860 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Articles of Interest and Statistics: clippings and manuscript, 1987-1997; id123861 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous/Influences, Articles and Notes, 1987-1992; id123862 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- New York City Guerrilla Girls, id123778
  This series contains two folders of clippings, articles, and protest materials from the original New York City group.
  - Guerrilla Girls N.Y. Backround Material: Photocopied correspondence and clippings (1 of 2), 1985-2000; id123864 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Guerrilla Girls N.Y. Backround Material: Transcripts and clippings (2 of 2), 1987-1992; id123865 (Box 10, Folder 24)
- Guerrilla/Gorilla Girls, Other Cities, id123779
  This series contains three folders of correspondence, protest material, brochures, and photographs that detail the activities of Guerrilla/Gorilla Girls in different parts of the United States.
  - Los Angeles and Chicago propaganda flyers, undated; id123867 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Dallas Guerrilla Girls’ correspondence, 1989; id123868 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Guerrilla Girls San Francisco correspondence, 1989; id123869 (Box 10, Folder 27)